Guide to the Extra-illustrated Life of Nollekens
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Letter to William Behnes., 1827 July 17; Kerrich, Richard Edward, 1801-1872; 3 pages; 23 x 19 cm. (Box 3-a)
  Correspondence; Monuments -- Great Britain; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823; Behnes, William, 1794-1864
- Printed testimonials to the competence of John Thomas Smith, gathered by him in pursuit of the post of drawing-master at Christ's Hospital. Signed by Smith., 1798 May 10; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833; 2 pages; 22.5 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-1)
  Correspondence; Art -- Study and teaching; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833; Christ's Hospital (London, England)
- Letter from William Ponsonby, Earl of Bessborough., 1768 August 9; Bessborough, William Ponsonby, Earl of, 1704-1793; 1 page; 23.5 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-2)
  Presenting compliments to Mr. Stanley about a bust left at his house in London by Mr. Stanley.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1828 November 9; Abbot, Charles, Baron Colchester, 1757-1829; 1 page; 23.5 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-3)
  Saying that he would be very pleased to receive a copy of the book on Nollekens.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1828 October 31; 4 pages; 19 x 11 cm. (Box 3-4)
  Acknowledging with gratitude and high praise Smith's book on Nollekens. Letter perhaps by Roper.
- Letter to William Upcott., 1828 October 30; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833; 2 pages; 23 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-5)
  Presenting a copy of his book on Nollekens; with a second copy for the London Institution, where Upcott was a sub-librarian from 1806 to 1834.
  Correspondence; London Institution; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823; Upcott, William, 1779-1845
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1827 January 1; Moyes, James; 2 pages; 18.5 x 11.5 cm. (Box 3-6)
  Saying that he has heard that he will have the printing of the book on Nollekens, and offering his thanks.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1829 November 19; Didbin, Thomas Frognall, 1776-1847; 2 pages; 18 x 12 cm. (Box 3-7)
  About packing up his pictures and mentioning several of them.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., undated; Morton, Andrew, 1802-1845; 2 pages; 18.5 x 11.5 cm. (Box 3-8)
  Praising his work on Nollekens.
  Correspondence; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., Rosebery, Archibald John Primrose, Earl of, 1783-1854; 1 page; 23 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-9)
  Asking him to stop sending newspapers to Dalmeny and to begin sending them to his London house.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1830 May 10; Brooksbank, Thomas; 1 page; 20 x 13 cm. (Box 3-10)
  Asking him to join him and some friends and the Crown & Sceptre in Greenwich next Saturday.
- Letter to the Secretary of the Royal Academy., [1841] April 20; Baring, Thomas, 1799-1873 (Box 3-11)
  About some pictures sent for exhibition.
  2 pages; 18 x 11.5 cm.
  Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Letter to Henry Howard., 1841 July 28; Baring, Thomas, 1799-1873; 1 page; 18.5 x 11 cm. (Box 3-12)
  Asking him to deliver to "Mr. Smith or bearer" the pictures listed in the previous letter.
  Correspondence; Howard, Henry, 1769-1847; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Letter presumably to John Thomas Smith., 1807 September 21; Vincent, J.; 2 pages; 20 x 16 cm. (Box 3-13[a])
  About books which he is sending him or has sent him, and enclosing a list of errata [not present].
- Letter presumably to William Upcott., 1817 April 13; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833; 1 page; 32 x 20 cm. (Box 3-13[b])
  Asking very urgently for the return of a model belonging to Mr. Planta (probably Joseph Planta, librarian at the British Museum) and a drawing by the late Mr. Alexander (probably William Alexander, of the British Museum).
  Correspondence; Alexander, William, 1767-1816; Upcott, William, 1779-1845; Planta, Joseph, 1744-1827
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., undated; Ponsonby, Frederick, 3rd Earl of Bessborough, 1758-1844; 1 page; 23 x 19 cm. (Box 3-14[a])
  Asking him to send a copy of the Nollekens book and to let him know the price so he can pay for it.
- Letter presumably to John Thomas Smith., undated; Westmacott, Richard, 1799-1872 (Box 3-14[b])
  With a list of the principal works of his father (Sir Richard Westmacott) and where they are to be found. Some are asterisked as "National Monuments."
  3 pages; 18.5 x 11 cm.
  Correspondence; Westmacott, Richard, Sir; Smith, John Thomas, 1766-1833
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., undated; Williams, R.; 2 pages; 18 x 22.5 cm. (Box 3-15)
  Saying that he will be extremely happy to take a copy of his book.
- Letter to Nollekens., 1775 November 25; Forrester, James, 1729-1775; 4 pages; 27.5 x 20 cm. (Box 3-16[a])
  The author is probably James Forrester, the Irish landscape artist at Rome. Long and detailed letter about British painters in Italy. Mentions James Barry. Also mentions a copy of Piranesi prints ordered by Nollekens and discusses the political situation, "I sincerely hope that England will triumph over her rebellious sons who indeed seem to deserve a heavy chastisement".
  Correspondence; Piranesi, Giovanni Battista, 1720-1778; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823; Barry, James, 1741-1806
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1826 June 13; Spurgeon, J. G.; 1 page; 23 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-16[b])
  Asking for a copy of the Nollekens book.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1826 June 14; Spurgeon, J. G.; 1 page; 22.5 x 19 cm. (Box 3-17)
  Asking for another copy of the Nollekens book.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., undated; Beechey, William, Sir, 1753-1839; 1 page; 18 x 23 cm. (Box 3-18)
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1828 November 22; Rutland, Mary Isabella, 1756-1831; 1 page; 19 x 22.5 cm. (Box 3-19[a])
  Ordering a copy of the Nollekens book.
- Receipt of payment to W.J. Fry for altering plate portrait of J. Nollekens and engraving plate portrait of Rev. W. Cox., 1816 June 10; Cadell & Davies; 1 page; 12 x 19 cm. (Box 3-19[b])
  Accompanied by bill for Cadell & Davies to pay thirty one pounds and ten shillings to Mr. Fry. Signed by J.A. Dean.
  Receipts (financial records); Fry, W.J.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1824 November 7; Sutherland, George Granville Leveson-Gower, Duke of, 1758-1833; 1 page; 18 x 23 cm. (Box 3-20[a])
- Letter to Joseph Nollekens., undated; Buonaintz; 1 page; 20 x 15 cm (Box 3-20[b])
  Asking that Mr. Tierney's place at the Academy dinner be given to the Polish Prince Bariatinsky.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1828 November 21; Somerset, Edward Adolphus Seymour, Duke of, 1804-1885; 1 page; 23 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3-21[a])
- Letter to Alexander Day., 1798 (?) October 31; Hervey, Frederick Augustus, 1730-1803; 1 page; 23 x 19 cm (Box 3-21[b])
  With plan of his galleries, one for pictures and the other for statues, also mentioning that "Here I have found a real treasure - tis a Milanese who in stucco imitates all marbles so perfectly as to deceive both the sight and the touch - he has properly succeeded at Sans Souci'. Berlin, 31 October.
  Correspondence; Day, Alexander, 1745-1841
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1828 November 5; Hammersley; 1 page; 20 x 12.5 cm (Box 3-22[a])
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1823 April 26; 1 page; 22.5 x 18.5 cm (Box 3-22[b])
  As one of Nollekens' executors, drawing his attention to Mr. Stanley of 21 Old Bond St., who sold Mr. Cosway's effects.
- Letter to Joseph Nollekens., [1810] July 4; Bessborough, William Ponsonby, Earl of, 1704-1793; 1 page; 18.5 x 11.5 cm (Box 3-23)
  Asking for an order to let Lady Bessborough see the exhibition.
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1829 June 15; Graves, Richard; 2 pages; 23 x 19 cm (Box 3-24)
  Regretting that he had "so much trouble about [receiving] my copy of Nollekens and his times".
- Letter to John Thomas Smith., 1828 December 10; Bridge, J. G.; 1 page; 18.5 x 22.5 cm (Box 3-25)
  Asking for two more volumes of Nollekens.
- Letter to Joseph Nollekens., 1812 August 2; Gregory, Richard; 1 page; 23 x 19 cm (Box 3-29)
  Informing him that the bust of Gregory's father (William Gregory, 1766-1840) has arrived safely.
  Correspondence; Gregory, William, 1766-1840; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823
- Copy of a notice in the Morning Chronicle, about Nollekens' will., 1823 April 29; 1 page; 22.5 x 18.5 cm (Box 3-34)
- Anonymous letter to John Thomas Smith., undated; 3 pages; 24.5 x 20 cm (Box 3-35)
  Saying that if he publishes a second edition of the book, he will find a more accurate and detailed account of the life of Thomas Banks in the Gentleman's Magazine for 1807 or 1808. With some anecdotes.
- Last will and testament of Captain John Nollekens (copy)., 1772 February 21; Nollekens, John, Captain; 4 pages; 22.5 x 18 cm (Box 3-36)
  Attested copy of his last will. Captain John Nollekens, of the East India Company's service in Bengal, may have been a brother of the sculptor.
  Wills; Nollekens, John, Captain
- Letter to the Lord Mayor Elect and the Sheriff., 1803 November 4; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823; 1 page; 8 x 12 cm (Box 3-37)
  To Peter Perchard? Apologizing for being unable to wait on them due to "not being sufficiently recovered from a severe indisposition".
  Correspondence; Perchard, Peter
- Letter to Mr. du Bourg., undated; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823; 1 page; 11.5 x 18.5 cm (Box 3-41)
  Reminding him that his rent is due. Written on the verso of a Royal Academy printed communication.
- Draft of letter to Lord Falmouth., 1806 September 22; Nollekens, Joseph, 1737-1823; 2 pages; 15 x 21 cm (Box 3-42)
  About the monument to "the late Mrs. Boswin" (i.e. Frances Evelyn Boscawen). On the verso of a printed Royal Academy notice.
  Correspondence; Boscawen, Frances Evelyn, 1719-1805; Falmouth, George Evelyn Boscawen, Viscount, 1758-1808
- Letter to Joseph Nollekens., 1812 May 9; 1 page; 21.5 x 18.5 cm (Box 3-47)
  Signed: Penrick (?). Asking him when the bust of his wife will be finished.
- William Walker, Esqr. Lecturer on the Eidouranion. Engraved by Ridley from a Miniature by Miss E. Barralt. Published as the Act directs Decr. 31, 1798 by Bernor & Hood, 31 Poultry., 1798 December 31; engraving; 16 x 11 cm (Box 3-48)
  Portrait of William Walker.
  Engravings; Walker, William
- The Revd. James Berresford author of the "Miseries of human life" & drawn in the Print-room of the British Museum for my friend J.T. Smith. Thomas Foster. May 19th 1823., 1823 May 19; engraving; 20 x 17.5 cm (Box 3-49)
  Portrait of Reverend James Berresford.
  Engravings; Berresford, James, Reverend
- Engraved portrait of Joseph Nollekens., undated; engraving; 19 x 13.5 cm (Box 3-50)
- Joseph Nollekens by F Chantrey 1816., engraving; 30.5 x 24 cm (Box 3-51)
- Nollekens. Engraved by Scriven, Historical Engraver to His Majesty., undated; engraving; 21.5 x 15 cm (Box 3-52)
- Charles Towneley. From a Bust by Nollekens in the Possession of John Towneley Esqr. T. Baxter delt. Northington sculp., undated; engraving; 19.5 x 12 cm (Box 3-53)
- Mr. Thomas Hope's Picture Gallery. No. 1. Duchess St. London. G. Cattermole del. J. Le Keux sc. London, Published by J. Warren, Old Rond St. May 1, 1821., 1821 May 1; engraving; 14 x 19.5 cm (Box 3-54)
  View of Thomas Hope's Picture Gallery.
  Engravings; Hope, Thomas, 1770?-1831
- West's Picture Gallery, Newman St. London. G. Cattermole del. J. Le Keux sc. Published by Sherwood Jones & Co. April 1st 1824., 1824 April 1; engraving; 14 x 20 cm (Box 3-55)
  View of West's Picture Gallery.
- View of the New Gallery Cleveland House. Engraved by William Bond, from a drawing by J.C. Smith. London: Published June 4 1808, by Longman, Hurst, Rees & Orme, Paternoster Row., 1808 June 4; engraving; 13.5 x 19 cm (Box 3-56)
  View of the New Gallery, Cleveland House.
  Engravings; Cleveland House (London, England)
- Earl of Granard. Wright del. Heath sculp. Published March 1, 1815 by G. Robinson, Paternoster Row, London., 1815 March 1; engraving; 30 x 25 cm (Box 3-57)
  Portrait of the George Formes, Sixth Earl of Granard.
  Engravings; Granard, George Forbes, Earl of, 1760–1837
- Joseph Planta Esqe. F. R. S. Engraved by W. Sharp from a Medallion by Pistrucci., undated; engraving; 20 x 14 cm (Box 3-58)
- Aaron Hill Esqe. Published by E Evans. No. 1. Great Queen Str. Lincoln's Inn Fields., undated; engraving; 23.5 x 17 cm (Box 3-59)
  Portrait of Aaron Hill.
  Engravings; Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750
- Thomas Otway. From a Picture by Riley in the possession of T. H. Prentice Esqr. Drawn by J. Thurston. Engraved by T. Bragg. London, Jany 1, 1821; Published by W. Walker, 8 Grays Inn Square., 1821 January 1; engraving; 30.5 x 24.5 cm (Box 3-60)
  Portrait of Thomas Otway.
  Engravings; Otway, Thomas, 1652-1685
- Lieut. Genl. Sir Ralph Abercromby, K. B. Painted by J. Hoppner, R.A. Engraved by H. D. Cook. Fisher, Son & Co. London, 1847., engraving; 27 x 21 cm (Box 3-61)
  Portrait of Sir Ralph Abercromby.
  Engravings; Abercromby, Ralph, Sir, 1734-1801
- James Barry Esqr. late R.A. European Magazine. From a Picture Painted by himself about the Year 1783. Engraved by Ridley & Holl. Published by J. Asperne at the Bible, Crown & Construction, 32 Cornhill. April 30, 1806., engraving; 21 x 13 cm (Box 3-62)
- A View of the House in which the late Mr. Barry resided, in Castle St. Oxford Road. T. Prattent del. et sculp. Published by J. Asperne at the Bible, Crown & Constitution, 32 Cornhill, 30 April 1806., 1806 April 30; engraving; 21 x 13 cm (Box 3-63)
- Residence of John Hoole, the translator of "Tasso" & "Ariosto". Great Queen Street Lincolns Inn Fields. C. J. Smith., undated; engraving; 28 x 22 cm (Box 3-64)
- J.F. Leicester. Sir Joshua Reynolds Pinxit. James Thomson sculp. London. Published for the Proprietors of the European Magazine by Lupton Relfe, 13 Cornhill August 1 1823., 1823 August 1; engraving; 19.5 x 13 cm (Box 3-65)
  Portrait of John Fleming Leicester, first Baron de Tabley.
  Engravings; De Tabley, John Fleming Leicester, Baron, 1762-1827
- The Hon. Daines Barrington. European Magazine. Engraved by Bromley, from a Painting by Drummond. Published J. Sewell, 32 Cornhill 1795., engraving; 21 x 13 cm (Box 3-66)
  Portrait of Daines Barrington.
  Engravings; Barrington, Daines, 1727-1800
- John Armstrong M.D. From a Miniature by Shelley in the possession of the Publisher. Drawn by J. Thurston. Engraved by F. Engleheart. London. May 1, 1821, Published by Walker, 8 Grays Inn Square., 1821 May 1; engraving; 24 x 16.5 cm (Box 3-67)
  Portrait of John Armstrong
  Engravings; Armstrong, John, 1709-1779
- Lady Duncannon. Walker delt. Mackenzie sc., undated; engraving; 12 x 8 cm (Box 3-68)
  Portrait of Lady Duncannon.
  Engravings; Bessborough, Henrietta Frances Spencer Ponsonby, Countess of, 1761-1821
- Charles Dibdin Esqr. European Magazine. Engraved by Ridley from an Original Painting by S. Drummond. Published by J. Asperne at the Bible, Crown & Constitution. Cornhill April 1, 1809., 1809 April 1; engraving; 21 x 13 cm (Box 3-69)
  Portrait of Charles Dibdin.
  Engravings; Dibdin, Charles
- Laurence Delvaux. W. Hibbart sculp., undated; engraving; 28 x 22 cm (Box 3-70)
  Portrait of Laurent Delvaux.
  Engravings; Delvaux, Laurent, 1696?-1778
- Mr. Edward Dayes, late Draughtsman to H.R.H. the Duke of York. E. Dayes pinxt. W. Holl sculp. Pub. 1805 for Mrs. Dayes, 42 Devonshire Street, Queen Square., engraving; 21 x 14.5 cm (Box 3-71)
  Portrait of Edward Dayes.
  Engravings; Dayes, Edward, 1763-1804
- Captain Thomas Coram. Hogarth pinxt. T. Cook & Son sculpt., undated; engraving; 15 x 11.5 cm (Box 3-72)
- Mrs. Cowly. Mackenzie, sc. Published Dec. 1 1801 by Vernor & Hood, Poultry., 1801 December 1; engraving; 17 x 10 cm (Box 3-73)
  Portrait of Mrs. (Hannah) Cowley.
  Engravings; Cowley, (Hannah), Mrs., 1743-1809
- Mrs. Cowley. Ridley & Holl sc. Pub by Vernor & Co., Poultry. Augst 1, 1806., 1806 August 1; engraving; 22 x 13 cm (Box 3-74)
- Mrs. Cowley. J. Chapman sc., undated; engraving; 10 x 7 cm (Box 3-75)
- Captain Cook. Roffe sc. Limbird Publisher 143 Strand., undated; engraving; 18 x 11 cm (Box 3-76)
  Portrait of James Cook.
  Engravings; Cook, James, 1728-1779
- The Right Honourable Charles Abbot, Baron Colchester, &c. Engraved by H. Meyer from an original Painting by S. Drummond Esq. R.A. London, Published for the European Magazine, by J. Asperne 32 Cornhill 1st Octr 1817., 1817 October 1; engraving; 21.5 x 13.5 cm (Box 3-77)
- Sir George Beaumont, Bart. From an original Picture by J. Hoppner, Esq. R.A. in the Possession of the Right Honble. Lord Mulgrave. Drawn by J. Wright, Engraved by J.S. Agar. Published Jan. 16, 1812 by T. Cadell & W. Davies, Strand, London., 1812 January 16; engraving; 31x 25 cm (Box 3-78)
  Portrait of Sir George Beaumont.
- Henry, Earl Bathurst. From an original Picture by T. Phillips, Esq. R.A. in the Possession of Sir George Thomas, Bart. Drawn by J. Wright, Engraved by H. Meyer. Published Nov. 21 1810 by T. Cadell & W. Davies, Strand, London., 1810 November 21; engraving; 33 x 25 cm (Box 3-79)
  Portrait of Henry Bathurst.
  Engravings; Bathurst, Henry Bathurst, Earl, 1714-1794
- Henry St. John, Viscount Bolinbroke OB. 1751. From the Original of Kneller, in the collection of the Right Honble. the Earl of Egremont. Engraved by W.T. Fry. The London Printing and Publishing Company., undated; engraving; 27 x 19 cm (Box 3-80)
  Portrait of Henry St. John.
  Engravings; Bolingbroke, Henry St. John, Viscount, 1678-1751
- Richard Owen Cambridge. Ozias Humphry, R.A. del. Edward Finden, sc. London, Published 1835 by John Murray. Albemarle Street., engraving; 22.5 x 15 cm (Box 3-81)
  Portrait of Richard Owen Cambridge.
  Engravings; Cambridge, Richard Owen, 1717-1802
- Miss Louisa Maria Carr. Engraved by H. Meyer from an original Miniature by C.F. Taylor. London, Published Sepr. 1 1824 for La Belle Assemblee No. 192., 1824 September 1; engraving; 19 x 12 cm (Box 3-82)
  Portrait of Louisa Maria Peach.
  Engravings; Peach, Louisa Maria, 19th century
- Sir Anthony Carlisle, F.R.S. President of the Royal College of Surgeons. Sir M.A. Shee. P.R.A. H. Robinson., undated; engraving; 16.5 x 10 cm (Box 3-83)
  Portrait of Anthony Carlisle.
  Engravings; Carlisle, Sir Anthony, 1768–1840
- Rubens (Pierre-Paul) Peintre + 1640. Galrie. Histque. de Versailles. Dessines par Girardet et L. Massard., undated; engraving; 20 x 14.5 cm (Box 3-84)
  Portrait of Peter Paul Rubens.
  Engravings; Rubens, Peter Paul, 1577-1640
- Frederick Earl of Carlisle, K.G. From an original Picture by J. Hoppner, R.A. in his Lordships Possession. Drawn by J. Jackson, Engraved by H. Meyer. Published March 12, 1814, by T. Cadell & W. Davies, Strand, London., 1814 March 12; engraving; 33 x 25 cm (Box 3-85)
  Portrait of Frederick Howard Earl of Carlisle.
- Materials towards a history of the arts of Painting, Sculpture, Engraving, and Architecture, in Great Britian; illustrated with autographs, portraits, drawings, and engravings; collected and arranged by Joseph Mayer, F.S.A. of Pennant House, Bebington; Formerly of Liverpool. Volume _____ 1875. J.E. Worrall, Liverpool., engraving; 30 x 25 cm (Box 3-86)
  Six copies of a page containing a variety of engraved images and text.
  Engravings; Mayer, Joseph, 1803-1886